All right folks next we talk about operators and expressions. Now what are
expressions in any programming language you can just think about them as being
let's say in Java or C++ or in C# or Python anything that can be evaluated to a
value right. So they can be for example if we just have a look at this
invitation you can just say 6 plus 9 this is an expression right you can even say
16 divided by 7 for example this is another expression so so these are all
expressions that can evaluate to a value that is 6 plus 9 you would say
would evaluate to a value that is 15 similarly you do the division for 16
divided by 7 you will again get a different value so that is about expressions
right so and then we come upon and expressions you can find them any anywhere or
everywhere in programming languages like in conditions loops or in method
bodies you'll find them everywhere right and then we would have this has
something to do with operators as well if you have a look at this thing here so
you can say this here is an operator similarly this here is an operator that
is the operator here is the plus this is the division and then we have some
operators in Java as with any of the programming language like for example we
have arithmetic operators and those are for example less you have minus you
have multiply you have divide and you have modulus as well right so now
obviously you will know that these require operands to be worked with right
on both the left and the right side with plus it just results in addition this
is a subtraction a multiplication and a division and the difference between the
modulus and the division is now if you sometimes have a requirement of using
the modulus operator it would give you not the cushion but the remainder of
things right and there are certain requirements or situations where we instead
of division we use this modulus operator as well and then we have some more
operators into the mix like we have comparison operators like you have less
than greater than less than equal to you have greater than equal to you have
a assignment operator and you have not equal to as well so these are what you
say is comparison operators and generally we use them with conditions wherever
you have to specify a condition be it in a if condition or a for loop or a
while or a do while or somewhere as I said where you require conditions to be
put in so for that fact we have the comparison operators that are these ones
here right the second ones so then you have the unary operators that is
plus plus and minus minus right which you use again for addition and
subtraction but use it only as with one operand rather than these ones which
require two operands to be used but these just require one operand either to
the left or the right and if you use it if you use let's say a variable with
the and then plus plus it becomes the post fix unary operator if you use the
operator first and then the operand it becomes the prefix unary operator
right so we'll have a look at those ones as well with some quick examples I'll
just head over back to intelligent IDE and what I'll do is this was user input
or Java we'll again say a new class inside my package that is org org for
now and I'll just call it operators work right again I'll just maximize this
for you for you to have a good look at this we have the main method we don't
need to write it completely as you know the IntelliSense in IntelliG has
always been one of its 40 right so starting with let's say I have a variable
there I just call it well and you can get user input from runtime as well and
I can instead of doing the scanner first and then the next int I can just do it
at this way like if I just have to use it at one line I'll say new scanner it
was imported once I hit enter dot next int right and so that the user knows why
the cursor is blinking so I'll just put in a sound and I'll just say enter a number
and the value would be taken into this variable that as well and then what I
can do is I can say well plus plus for example for starting with I can just say
well plus 10 and I can assign it through the same variable well or if my
requirement is different then I can assign it to a different variable that
depends on the requirement I say always say programming is requirement
driven it doesn't depend on the mood that you are in today right it doesn't
depend on what you're feeling like but it's always requirement driven whatever
user require your requirement is those kind of tools you're going to use I'm
just going to tell you about the different tools that are available for you in
the Java programming language like these operators but then it's upon you how
and where you would use them right so for example now my requirement is I just
want to add 10 with the number that the user entered at on time and then
assign it to the same variable and then I'll just say sound and I'll just print
in the value I'll hit quickly control R and you're seeing enter a number I'll
say 210 and you're seeing 220 right so this 10 was added to well and it did
the job similarly try your stuff out with the minus multiply divide and
modulus for divide let's do it because there's a difference if you said well
divided by 10 I'll just say run and then you say three forty nine and you got
thirty four right because three forty nine was divided by ten and once you do
that we got thirty four but if you had done the modulus just have a look at
the difference it would have made again hit run so again I'll say three forty
nine and you just got nine right so that's the difference between the divide
and the modulus this time also three forty nine was divided by ten and ten
usually say thirty four into ten is three forty and you got the remainder in
this case that is that is nine and for a classic program like reverse of any
number that the user interests on time we need the modules right we can't do
stuff there with the divide right that is something you can just try out after
this video as an exercise that is just take a number from user run time and
then calculate and print it servers okay so that's a difference and but if
you would just want it to shorten this a bit right because see we should
always try to write a succent precise code but only after we learn the
fundamentals well first do it the longer way that's my advice that's my
suggestion always to all the learners in my sessions but once you have got a
hold of the longer way then always try to do things the shorter way the more
succinct way the less were was way right and if you would have wanted to do
this you could have just shortened it by just saying something like this that
is modulus is equal to that is a compound operator here right these are all
compound operators right what does this do is it first modulus that device
sets and just puts in the result into this variable similarly we have plus
equal to we have minus equal to we have multiplied equal to as well these are
all compound operators why are they called compound operators because they do
more the one operation at the same time it multiplies as well as a sign and in
our case it does the modulus and then does the assignment as well these are
compound operators right and then I was telling you we can too that is let's
just comment this out for now I can do the unary operator weekly I'll say
well plus plus right and they'll use do a sound and I'll just say well so what
happens is it just gets the value from memory that would be what I would have
entered at runtime then if there was an associated operation on this line it
would have done that first and then the addition right that's why it's called
post fix right so a rule of thumb or the thing that makes you remember this is
post fix says it gets the value from memory then first does the associated
operation first if there was any on line number 16 there is no there is no
associated operation right it's simple but I'll just shortly make it do so and
then does the addition but on the other hand if it was like this that is the
prefix then it would do the get the memory value first then do the addition and
then the associated value that's why it's called prefix do it first and then do
the associated operation but here you should remember on line number 16 plus
plus well or if you would write like this this doesn't make any difference it
just adds it because there is it's just a singular operation just run this
out and you say 230 becomes 31 but if you would have written this the other way
it would still give you 231 see but now if you would have done something like
this and this would make it clear to you I have just used this unary operator
within a print ln and if said print ln plus plus well what would it do now is
if I enter 230 or any number it would get that but first do the increment in
the memory update that in the memory and then do the print ln so you'll get the
updated value let's have a look at that so I'll say 231 gets gives you
232 but if you would have done the post fix with minus minus or plus plus
with just using plus plus as an example and you will see now you will only get
the value that is not updated you will get the older value what does it do it
gets the value from the memory what is that in the memory then first does the
associated operation and then increments in the memory let's have a look at this
they should still give me 231 but in the memory it's 232 now and you can get a
proof of that by just saying control D just print well now see say 231 say
first 231 but in the memory it was 232 right that's how prefix and post
fix work right similarly we have other operators as I said that that is less
than we have less than equal to we have greater than we have greater than equal to
and we have assignment operator and we have not equal to as well but these are
comparison operators generally we use them with in a condition generally not
always but generally I'll just say these are comparison operators and then you
have logical operators for combining multiple conditions like and you have or
and you have not and you have a variety of these as well with the singular and
and with the singular or that is the short circuit and and the short circuit or
and this is the non short circuit and in the short circuit or and there is a
significant difference in how they work and more on that in the next video with
how these work in conditions and these ones but before that obviously we
need to know how does if else or particularly how does if work in Java to get
you started with writing conditions even if you're coming from a different
language what is same here what is similar and what is different what are the
varieties in Java when it comes to when it comes to writing conditions